Guillem Martí-Devesa CV

Astroparticle Physicist from Barcelona, Spain (age: 28)

Current Position: Universitätsassistent – Postdoc at Universität Innsbruck

Fields: Astroparticle Physics, Gamma-Ray Astronomy

Coding: Python, C, Fortran, R, Java

Languages: Catalan, Spanish, English, German Tools: Fermitools, XSPEC, git, Tempo2, LATEX

Technikerstraße 25, 8/10
Innsbruck, Austria
guillem.marti-devesa@uibk.ac.at
+43 677 627 797 26

Summary

Astroparticle physicist, member of the *Fermi* Large Area Telescope (*Fermi* LAT) and the High Energy Stereoscopic System (H. E. S. S.) Collaborations.

Expertise on Galactic Astroparticle Physics, particularly in stellar systems – binaries and stellar clusters – using multi-wavelength data (optical, X-ray, and γ ray). Main methods employed: Maximum-Likelihood Estimation and Time-Series Analysis.

Education

PhD in Physics - Universität Innsbruck, Austria

2017 - 2020

- · Thesis: Observational Studies on the Population of Binaries in the Gamma-Ray Sky
- · Doctoral schools at DIAS-DCU (Ireland), LAPP-CNRS (France) and ECAP-FAU (Germany). Radio analysis workshops by JIVE (Netherlands) and UK ARC-UM (United Kingdom)

MSc in Astro-, Particle Physics and Cosmology - Universitat de Barcelona, Spain

2016 - 2017

- · Thesis: First Multi-Filter Photometric Monitoring of the Be-BH System MWC 656
- · Courses on Statistics and Programming at ICCUB

BSc in Physics - Universitat de Barcelona, Spain

2012 - 2016

- · Thesis: Light Pollution in Barcelona: Night Sky Background Analysis
- · Observations performed at COU (Lleida, Spain) and Calar Alto (Almería, Spain)

Professional Degree in Music - Conservatori de Música de Barcelona, Spain

2008 - 2014

- · Honour Commendations in Chamber Music (2014) and Viola (2014)
- · Since then, concerts performed in Spain (Barcelona, Valencia, Pamplona, and others), Austria (Innsbruck), France (Toulouse), Germany (Steingaden), and Italy (Dobbiaco)

Work Experience

Universitätsassistent - Postdoc - Universität Innsbruck, Austria

2020 - present

- · LAT's Galactic Science Group co-coordinator since September 2022
- · Teaching between 4 and 6 hours weekly every semester
- · Journal referee for The Astrophysical Journal and Astronomy & Astrophysics

Graduate researcher - Universität Innsbruck, Austria

2017 - 2020

- · Member of the Fermi-LAT and H.E.S.S. collaborations (2018-Now)
- · One-month shift at H.E.S.S. site (Namibia), and remote data quality monitoring shifts with H.E.S.S. and Fermi-LAT

Researcher assistant - Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya, Spain

2015 - 2017

- · Studies on light pollution in natural reserves
- · Participation in the LoNNe calibration campaign in 2016 at COU observatory

Teaching

PR: Practical training course; PS: Exercise course; SE: Seminar; VO: Lecture; VU: Lecture-exercise course

At Universität Innsbruck	2021 - present
· PR Programming for Physics Students	BSc - Summer 2021 & 22 & 23
· PS Physics IV: Nuclear and Particle Physics	BSc - Summer 2021 & 22
· VU Astroparticle Physics I	MSc - Fall 2021/22
· PR Laboratory for Computational Physics A	MSc - Fall 2021/22 & 21/22
· VU Binary Systems in Astrophysics (new creation)	MSc - Fall 2021/22
· PS Physics I: Mechanics and Thermodynamics	BSc - Fall 2022/23
· VO Introduction to Astroparticle Physics	BSc - Fall 2022/23
· SE Bachelor Thesis Seminar (Astroparticle and Particle Physics coordinator)	BSc - 2023
· VU Astroparticle Physics II	MSc - Summer 2023
· VU Theoretical Astrophysics	MSc - Summer 2023

Supervision

Bachelor Theses

· High-Energy Gamma-Rays from the Omega Nebula – Daniel Resch	Summer 2021
· Gamma-Ray Flares of the Microquasar Cygnus X-3: a Fermi-LAT Perspective – Mike Wettke	Summer 2022
· Understanding the High-Energy Emission from the Omega Nebula – Sandrino Achenreiner	Summer 2022
· The Crab Nebula seen by H.E.S.S. and Fermi-LAT with Open-Source Tools – Melanie Federer [†]	ongoing
· The PWN MHS 15-52 as seen with H.E.S.S. and Fermi-LAT – Lukas Sabathil [†]	ongoing
· Neutrinos from Colliding Stellar Winds – Bernhard Lang	ongoing
· Anisotropic Inverse Compton from Cygnus X-1 – Philipp Aichner	ongoing

Master Theses

· Star Forming Regions as Hadronic Cosmic-Ray Accelerators – Nadine Bourriche* 2021 – 2022

Granted observing time

Proposals

NICER Cycle 5 (PI: Martí-Devesa, #6127, Priority A, 120 ks): Wind-wind interaction and par-	2023
ticle acceleration in the Kleinmann Star trapezium system. Additional NuSTAR time (50ks)	

· H.E.S.S. internal call (PI: Olivera-Nieto, #P2021-007, Priority A/B, 100h): Observation proposal of the microquasar SS 433

· Other H.E.S.S. internal proposals (co-author, information not public)

Talks

Conferences

· VGGRS Workshop VI, Innsbruck, Austria (invited talk & LOC)	April 2023
· Cosmic Magnetism in Void and Filaments, Bologna, Italy	January 2023
· Gamma 2022, Barcelona, Spain	July 2022
· 9th Fermi Symposium, Johannesburg, South Africa (Virtual)	April 2021
· VGGRS Workshop V, Barcelona, Spain	September 2019

Invited seminars

· ICCUB Seminar, Barcelona, Spain September 2022

· MPIK's Astrophysics Seminar, Heidelberg, Germany (Virtual)

July 2021

2021

2020, 2021, 2023

[†] Co-supervised with Dr. Markus Holler

^{*} Co-supervised with Prof. Olaf Reimer

Outreach

Activities

· Cloud chamber experiment and Sun observations with high-school students

ICCUB - Jan 2017

Talks

· Understanding the Universe: Astroparticle Physics in Tirol

Mittelschule 2 Wörgl - Oct 2022

Publications

Short authorlist journal publications

- [1] P. Da Vela*, **G. Martí-Devesa**, F. G. Saturni, P. Veres, A. Stamerra and F. Longo. "Intergalactic magnetic field studies by means of γ -ray emission from GRB 190114C". In: *PRD* 107, 6 (Mar. 2023), p. 063030. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.107.063030. arXiv: 2303.03137 [astro-ph.HE].
- [2] **G. Martí-Devesa***, O. Reimer, and A. Reimer. "Limits on the non-thermal emission of the WR-WR system Apep". In: *A&A* 670, L6 (Feb. 2023), p. L6. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202245332. arXiv: 2212.10146 [astro-ph.HE].
- [3] C. C. Cheung*, T. J. Johnson*, P. Jean*, M. Kerr, K. L. Page, J. P. Osborne, A. P. Beardmore, K. V. Sokolovsky, F. Teyssier, S. Ciprini, **G. Martí-Devesa**, I. Mereu, S. Razzaque, K. S. Wood, S. N. Shore, S. Korotkiy, A. Levina and A. Blumenzweig. "Fermi LAT Gamma-ray Detection of the Recurrent Nova RS Ophiuchi during its 2021 Outburst". In: *ApJ* 935.1, 44 (Aug. 2022), p. 44. DOI: 10.3847/1538-4357/ac7eb7. arXiv: 2207.02921 [astro-ph.HE].
- [4] **G. Martí-Devesa*** and O. Reimer. " η Carinae with Fermi-LAT: two full orbits and the third periastron". In: A&A 654, A44 (Oct. 2021), A44. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202140451. arXiv: 2109.05950 [astro-ph.HE].
- [5] **G. Martí-Devesa*** and O. Reimer. "X-ray and γ -ray orbital variability from the γ -ray binary HESS J1832-093". In: A&A 637, A23 (May 2020), A23. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202037442. arXiv: 2001.02701 [astro-ph.HE].
- [6] **G. Martí-Devesa***, O. Reimer, J. Li and D. F. Torres. "Hints of γ -ray orbital variability from γ^2 Velorum". In: A&A 635, A141 (Mar. 2020), A141. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202037462. arXiv: 2001.02708 [astro-ph.HE].

Reports in The Astronomer's Telegram

- [7] T. J. Johnson*, J. B. Coley, **G. Martí-Devesa**, R. H. D. Corbet, C. C. Cheung, M. Kerr, A. B. Pearlman, J. Hare and Z. Wadiasingh. "Continuing >100 MeV Activity from the PSR B1259-63/LS 2883 System 85 Days Post-periastron Detected with the Fermi-LAT". In: *The Astronomer's Telegram* 14612 (May 2021), p. 1.
- [8] T. J. Johnson, **G. Martí-Devesa**, and C.C. Cheung*. "Detection of enhanced emission above 100 MeV, using Fermi-LAT data, associated with the PSR B1259-63/LS 2883 binary system approximately 60 days after periastron". In: *The Astronomer's Telegram* 14540 (Apr. 2021), p. 1.

Complete list of publications on ADS or Orcid ©